James T. Farrell Collection
James T. Farrell Collection
1953-1961
Farrell, James T. (James Thomas), 1904-1979.
1 folder (SC)
Papers of the American novelist, author. Collection includes lecture notes on the poetry of Horace Gregory; manuscripts of articles; and published material by and about Farrell.
148973
Biographical History
James T. Farrell (1904-1979) was an Irish-American novelist, short story writer, journalist, travel writer, poet, and literary critic. Born and raised in Chicago, Illinois, he attended the University of Chicago and published his first short story in 1929. He is best known for his Studs Lonigan trilogy and for his A note on Literary Criticism, in which he described two types of the American Marxist character.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The James T. Farrell Papers consist almost exclusively of writings, including lecture notes, manuscripts of articles, and published material. The latter includes newspaper and magazine articles by and about Farrell.
Arrangement of the Collection
Writings are arranged alphabetically by title.
Related Material
See also the
Jack Robbins Collection Relating to James T. Farrell
.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- American Fiction; Literature -- American Poetry; Farrell, James T. (James Thomas), 1904-1979.; Gregory, Horace, 1898-1982.; American literature -- 20th century.; Authors, American.; Novelists, American.; Manuscripts for publication.; Clippings (information artifacts); Photographs.; Authors.; Novelists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Purchased.
Inventory
- Writings
  - "Author defends his character Studs Lonigan," Louisville Times, Nov 22 1960 (Sc 20)
  - "A chance meeting with Mencken and masters", Jan 31 1956 (Sc 20)
  - "A few observations on movie and television files", undated (Sc 20)
  - "Horace Gregory's poetry reread, undated; lecture notes (Sc 20)
  - "Lebanon: a first impression" (Sc 20)
  - "Open letter to Khrushchev," Thought, Dec 2 1961 (Sc 20)
  - "Terrence McGinty", 1953; short story (Sc 20)
- Miscellaneous
  - "High hopes that led to disillusion," New York Times, Nov 12 1961 (Sc 20)
  - Photograph of Farrell, Horace Gregory, and Marya Zaturenska, 1979 (Sc 20)